<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sidath Munasinghe</title>
    <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sidath Munasinghe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sidathasiri.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Maximizing Cloud Infrastructure Efficiency with AWS CDK and Terraform</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2024/06/22/Unleashing-the-Power-of-CDK-and-Terraform-in-Cloud-Deployments/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2024/06/22/Unleashing-the-Power-of-CDK-and-Terraform-in-Cloud-Deployments/</guid>
      <description>Deploying applications to the cloud has become a cornerstone of modern software development. AWS offers CloudFormation as a service to facilitate cloud deployments and tools like the AWS Cloud Development Kit (CDK). At the same time, Terraform has emerged as a powerful solution for Infrastructure as Code (IaC), enabling faster deployments to multiple cloud providers. In this article, we’ll explore the benefits of using AWS CDK and Terraform together and walk through a practical example of creating a REST API with CDK in TypeScript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI on AWS with Amazon Bedrock Service</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2024/05/01/Generative-AI-on-AWS-with-Amazon-Bedrock/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2024/05/01/Generative-AI-on-AWS-with-Amazon-Bedrock/</guid>
      <description>Amazon Bedrock is a managed service that provides high-performing foundation models (FMs) from leading AI companies using a single interface. With Bedrock, we don’t need to worry about hosting and managing the infrastructure for the foundation models. We can directly jump into consuming these models with its APIs and start building apps. Further, we can customize these foundation models to fit our use cases and also integrate them with knowledge bases and agents to provide enhanced features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effortless Kubernetes Infrastructure Provisioning and Application Deployment with Cluster.dev and Helm Charts</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2024/02/17/Deploy-Kubernetes-in-Minutes:-Effortless-Infrastructure-Creation-and-Application-Deployment-with-Cluster.dev-and-Helm-Charts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2024/02/17/Deploy-Kubernetes-in-Minutes:-Effortless-Infrastructure-Creation-and-Application-Deployment-with-Cluster.dev-and-Helm-Charts/</guid>
      <description>Kubernetes has quickly become the leading orchestration tool for containerized applications, celebrated for its ability to scale applications robustly and resiliently. Its success lies in a powerful framework that adeptly handles the complex life cycles of distributed applications. Yet, deploying Kubernetes cluster infrastructure, essential for tapping into this platform’s capabilities, presents significant challenges. This complexity requires considerable effort and poses a major hurdle for many seeking to leverage Kubernetes for scalable application deployment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature Flags on AWS Using AppConfig for Seamless Software Evolution</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/12/20/Harnessing-Feature-Flags-on-AWS-AppConfig-for-Seamless-Software-Evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/12/20/Harnessing-Feature-Flags-on-AWS-AppConfig-for-Seamless-Software-Evolution/</guid>
      <description>In the fast-paced realm of software development, agility and adaptability are not just a virtue but a necessity. Feature flagging is a versatile technique that offers a strategic approach for releasing features to end users, enabling rapid software development while giving more control to teams to evolve products.
Feature flags decouple feature deployment from code deployment, allowing teams to release features incrementally and independently. Due to this, teams can do frequent code deployments darkly, although the entire feature development is incomplete.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a WebSocket API on AWS</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/10/15/Building-WebSocket-APIs-with-AWS-API-Gateway-and-CDK/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/10/15/Building-WebSocket-APIs-with-AWS-API-Gateway-and-CDK/</guid>
      <description>In the continuously evolving landscape of web applications, real-time communication has become the gold standard for creating engaging and interactive user experiences. Whether you’re building a chat application, a collaborative online game, or a live dashboard, WebSocket technology has emerged as the enchanting solution that makes real-time magic happen. And when it comes to unleashing the full potential of WebSockets in a serverless and scalable manner, Amazon Web Services (AWS) has a spell of its own — AWS API Gateway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secure Deployments to AWS with GitHub Actions via OpenID Connect</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/03/04/Secure-Cloud-Deployments-to-AWS-with-GitHub-Actions-using-OpenID-Connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/03/04/Secure-Cloud-Deployments-to-AWS-with-GitHub-Actions-using-OpenID-Connect/</guid>
      <description>GitHub Actions is a platform to perform automated tasks upon triggering an event in GitHub. This is being used extensively to govern continuous integration and continuous delivery (CI/CD) workflows once code changes are pushed to a repository. But GitHub Actions has capabilities beyond that to automate a lot of stuff such as tagging releases, sending notifications when creating issues, repository migrations, etc.
Why GitHub Actions for CI/CD? There are several benefits to using GitHub Actions for Continuous Integration and Continuous Deployment (CI/CD):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AWS CDK for Seamless Infrastructure Management</title>
      <link>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/01/20/Seamless-Infrastructure-Management-with-AWS-CDK/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sidathasiri.github.io/2023/01/20/Seamless-Infrastructure-Management-with-AWS-CDK/</guid>
      <description>The heart of any software solution is its infrastructure and administering it appropriately is very crucial. At present, it can be seen that the majority of software vendors have moved towards using cloud platforms and serverless architectures to mitigate the complexity of maintaining infrastructure. Still, things like provisioning the infrastructure in diverse environments and keeping them in sync need enormous effort if done manually.
This challenge can be eased by a practice known as Infrastructure as code (IaC) that codifies and manages underlying IT infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
